A Guide to the Calvin T. Lucy Papers 1914-1978
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Calvin T. Lucy Papers 1914-1978
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 172
18.75 linear feet
Calvin T. Lucy
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department by Mr. Lucy's family after his death. An additional .25 feet of material was donated by C.T. Lucy, Jr. in 1993.
Biographical Information
Born in Baltimore, MD, on 8 October 1891, Calvin T. Lucy was educated at Baltimore City College (a public high school for boys) and graduated in 1909. While taking night school classes at BCC in commercial subjects, Lucy also worked at Crown Cork and Seal (1909-1912) in Baltimore. In 1912 he took a job with Reed Tobacco Company (a subsidiary of Laurus and Co.) as office manager and book keeper. Promoted in 1918 to general office manager for Laurus, Lucy left this position to serve in the army during World War I. He resumed his career with Laurus after his discharge and steadily advanced in management.
Given the responsibility of establishing a radio station in Richmond, in 1925, Lucy served as announcer, writer, producer, performer and general manager during the early years of WRVA. Non-commercial until 1928, WRVA then became an affiliate of NBC and C.T. moved into the sales and advertising portion of the operation. He supervised and managed the 5 kw station established in 1929; the 50 kw in 1938, and subsequently rose to Vice President with responsibility for radio and television.
Lucy was active in the broadcasting profession and was an early member of the National Association of Broadcasters. He was the first president of the Virginia Association of Broadcasters and the original chair of the (CBS) Columbia Affiliates Advisory Board. An active citizen in the Richmond community, Lucy was also a member of the Community Fund, the Scottish Rite Masons, the Chamber of Commerce, and of St. Mark's Episcopal Church and its governing body.
Lucy retired from the Laurus Company in 1961 and moved from Richmond to his farm near Ladysmith, VA. During his retirement he played a key role in the establishment of educational television in Richmond by providing technical assistance and served as a general consultant for the project. In 1973 C.T. received an award from the Virginia Association of Broadcasters. Mr. Lucy died on 16 May 1980.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of Mr. Lucy's personal correspondence, church files and mementos. Mr. Lucy's professional records for the Laurus Company and WRVA Radio-Television in Richmond, Virginia comprised a large portion of the collection. The materials cover the years 1914 to 1978. Also included in the collection are documents concerning the establishment of educational television in Virginia, several phonograph records, news clippings photographs and travel/historical brochures on Virginia.
Additional personal and professional materials can be found at the Virginia Historical Society.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged in chronological order.
Organization
The collection was received partially jumbled and at some point an arrangement was begun by the department but was never completed. The ordering of the collection was begun again in December 1986 and is comprised of the following Series: I-Personal Information and Correspondence 1914-1975; Series II-Church membership 1954-1969; Series III-Correspondence 1916-1978; Series IV-WRVA Radio (program, broadcast and publicity materials) 1926-1961; Series V-WRVA Radio Managerial materials; Series VI--WRVA TV 1952-1968; Series VII-Central Virginia Educational Television (CVETV) 1961-1963; Series VIII--Historical Publications and Materials; Series IX--Miscellaneous n.d.
Additional ordering, photocopying of news clippings and separation of the photographs from the collection will take place as time and staff permit. Several scrapbooks which were donated at a later date by Mr. Lucy's son are located in the oversize area with other scrapbooks.
Contents List
- Personal Information and Correspondence 1914-1975
  - Broadcast Pioneers information (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Bryd, Harry Flood Sr. file (Box-folder 1:2)
  - CBS Affiliate Advisory Board 1951 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - CBS Affiliate Convention (Box-folder 1:4)
  - CBS Report: Death of F.D.R. April 12, 1945 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Larus and Brothers Co. letters and history (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Mixcellaneous--personal (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Miscellaneous--personal (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1:10)
  - National Association of Broadcasters (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Postcards !920's-1950's (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Radio Stars of Today (Box-folder 1:13)
  - State Fair materials--WRVA 1968 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Tobacco prices (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Tobacco prices and labels (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters award 1973 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Church membership 1954-1969
  - St. Mark's 1954-1960 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - St. Mark's 1956-1961 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - St. Mark's Expansion Committee 1958 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - St. Mark's Building Committee 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - St. Mark's Property Committee 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - St. Mark's Talley sheets and deposit slips 1963 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Diocesan Missionary Society of Virginia 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - St Mark's Episcopal Church material (Box-folder 2:3)
  - National Council of Churches (black manifesto) (Box-folder 2:4)
- Correspondence 1916-1978
  - Miscellaneous 1916-1917, 1940, 1941 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence 1953-1961 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Retirement letters 1961 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence 1961 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence 1963 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Correspondence 1964 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Correspondence 1965 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Correspondence 1966 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Correspondence 1970 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Correspondence 1970 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Correspondence 1971 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Correspondence 1972 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Correspondence 1973 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Correspondence 1974 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Correspondence 1975 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Correspondence 1976 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Correspondence 1977 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Correspondence 1977 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Correspondence 1978 (Box-folder 3:3)
- WRVA Radio 1926-1961
  - 50,000 kw dedication March 17, 1939 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Anniversary publications, etc. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Anniversary programs 1950-1953 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - 30th anniversary Special Feature 1955 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - 30th anniversary publicity and promotion (Box-folder 3:8)
  - 30th anniversary complete program and celebration (Box-folder 3:9)
  - 30th anniversary WRVA (Box-folder 3:10)
  - 35th anniversary (Box-folder 3:11)
  - 50th anniversary revision sheets (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Annual reports, financial agreements, advertising policies 1937-1947 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Apple Blossom Festival 1936 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Book: All About Amos 'n' Andy, (removed from collection and catalogged 1929 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Citations for public service (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Commemorative booklets (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Commercials/public service announcements (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Corn Cob Pipe Club 1926-1936 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Corner Stone Material (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Dialogue 1934-1936 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Dialogue and Daily Radio program 1934-1936 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Dialogue 1937-1938 (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Dialogue 1939 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Dialogue 1940 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Dialogue 1941 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Dialogue 1942 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Dialogue 1943 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Dialogue 1944 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Dialogue 1945 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Dialogue 1946 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Dialogue 1947 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Dialogue 1948 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Dialogue 1949 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Dialogue 1950 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Dialogue 1951 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Dialogue 1952 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Dialogue 1953 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Dialogue 1954 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Dialogue 1955 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Dialogue 1956 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Early Program Notes (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Editorial Opinions (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Historical information (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Historical material (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Historical material (Box-folder 4:22)
  - History (rough draft), History of WRVA Broadcasting by Lucy (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Manager meeting minutes 1961-1964 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Memos and Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4:25)
  - Periodicals: Broadcasting; Richmond Magazine Nov. 15, 1935; Mar. 1931 (Box-folder 4:26)
  - Publicity 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4:27)
  - Promotional material 1935 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Radio Scripts--Historical events, Virginia History (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Radio Speech materials 1937-1946 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Radio Speech materials 1937-1946 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Special broadcasts "Meet America" (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Talent and speakers--Corn Cob Pipe Club 1925-1929 (Box-folder 5:6)
- WRVA Managerial materials
  - Application for 50 kw station (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Audience survey 1947-1950 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Walter R. Bishop file (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Coverage maps 1925-1940 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Disaster plan 1957 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Notes for speeches to employees n.d.,; names of employees 1928,1940-1961 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Obituaries (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Program log 1925-1928 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Program log 1929-1930 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Program log 1931-1932 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Promotional material (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Radio/Television surveys 1950-1954 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Reports, memoranda, 1934-1940 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Sales and trends charts 1963-1967 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Studio guest passes WWII (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Transmitter (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Wage scales 1943-1953 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - WMBG program sheets 1937-1942 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Wooden radio tower 1935 (Box-folder 7:9)
- WRVA Television 1952-1968
  - Department manager meeting minutes 1961-1964 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - FCC application 1952-1953 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - FCC application 1953 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - FCC Television hearing worksheets 1953 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - General memos 1962-1965 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Richmond television 1955-1956 (Box-folder 7:14)
  - Sales trends and charts 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7:15)
  - Television equipment (Box-folder 7:16)
  - Television logs 1959-1966 (Box-folder 7:17)
- Central Virginia Educational Television 1961-1963
  - Central Virginia Educational Television (CVETV) 1961 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - CVETV 1963-1976 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - CVETV 1977-1978 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - CVETV incorporation; correspondence 1961; 1962-1963 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Application material and correspondence 1962 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Board of Directors 1962-1964 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Completed FCC application 1963 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Correspondence--Thomas C. Boushall 1963 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Correspondence--Charles F. Duvall 1961 (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Correspondence--Charles F. Duvall 1963-1964 (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Correspondence--W.T. Reed 1961 (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Correspondence--re B.W. Spiller (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Correspondence--D.C. Woods 1962 (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Equipment proposals 1962-1963 (Box-folder 8:14)
  - FCC questionaire for directors (Box-folder 8:15)
  - General Electric proposal (Box-folder 8:16)
  - HEW Conference on ETV 1963 (Box-folder 8:17)
  - National Educational television--publications 1962 (Box-folder 8:18)
  - RCA proposals 1962 (Box-folder 8:19)
  - Revenue estimates; correspondnece with H Willett; FCC application support 1962-1963 (Box-folder 8:20)
  - Studies; reports 1962-1964 (Box-folder 8:21)
  - Technical correspondence 1962-1964 (Box-folder 8:22)
  - Tower and facilities costs 1962 (Box-folder 8:23)
- Historical Publications and materials
  - History--miscellaneous publications (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Miscellaneous Virginia history publications (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Richmond and Virginia-maps and pamphlets (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Richmond history (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Civil War centennial (Box-folder 9:5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Photographs, clippings, phonograph records, earmuffs (gag Christmas gift) (Box 10-11)
  - Certificate of Membership Broadcast Pioneers 1963 (Box 10-11)
  - Preview edition of LIFE magazine, Sept. 24, 1936
  - Cartoon (original) by Webster, March 5, 1932
  - Certificate presented to Lucy from the Virginia Association of Broadcasters 1958
  - Photograph: Acca Temple Chanters 1925
  - Photograph: Amos n' Andy arriving in Richmond Feb., 1933
  - Photograph: WRVA Radio Staff Christmas party 1948
  - Western Union telegram: congratulations on WRVA's 16th birthday, n.d.
  - Scrapbook 1933-1937 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1927-1929 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1925-1926 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1961-1975 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 1929-1932 (Box 6)